Chukwuma Onyeka Emordi

■ emordichukwuma@gmail.com

+2348145506446

Lagos, Nigeria

in www.linkedin.com/in/chukwuma-emordi

Profile

Highly motivated process engineer transitioning to backend development. Leveraging 5+ years at Dangote Petroleum Refinery, I developed meticulous problem-solving skills. Boot camp trained in JavaScript, Python, and C. Eager to leverage analytical skills and passion for technology to contribute to a software development team.

Professional Experience

2023/07 – present USA

Code Instructor

CodetheDream

- Volunteered as a coding mentor, enhancing the skills of aspiring software engineers.
- Mentored and guided project teams in code reviews.
- Facilitated meetings with project teams to address inquiries and provide solution.

2018/12 – present Nigeria

Principal Process/Production Engineer - RFCC unit

Dangote Petroleum Refinery and Petrochemical (DPRP)

- Conducted routine inspections and audits of the FCC Unit equipment and processes to identify and resolve operational issues.
- Collaborated with maintenance and engineering teams to develop and implement strategies for equipment reliability and maintenance optimization.
- Provided technical expertise and support for troubleshooting and resolving process upsets or abnormalities in the FCC Unit.
- Reviewed operating procedures, process documentation, and reports related to FCC Unit operations.

Senior Process Engineer - Utility

January 2021 - December 2023

- Played a key role in optimizing manufacturing processes, resulting in 15% improvement in efficiency and 10% reduction in operational costs.
- Led the commissioning and operations of key utility units, enhancing overall plant productivity and reducing downtime.
- Ensured compliance with safety standards by coordinating Pre-Start Up Safety Reviews (PSSR), loop testing, and SAT for the Firewater Unit.
- Facilitated smooth project transitions by reviewing and approving commissioning dossiers, signing "Ready for Start-Up" and handover certificates
- Minimized downtime and ensured smooth transitions by providing essential process support during pre-commissioning, commissioning, start-up, operations, and shutdown.
- Enhanced operational efficiency and safety by participating in the development of Management of Change (MOC) procedures and Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs).
- Provided training and mentorship to engineers, improving team performance and process safety compliance.
- Scheduled meetings with production managers to discuss and assess existing processes, determining risks of malfunctions and failures.
- Ensured safe work practices by acting as the Isolating Authority (IA) and endorsing work permits.
- Participated in technical reviews (HAZOP, Safety reviews, P&ID reviews, GA drawing reviews etc) of existing plant facilities to identify potential hazards and implement preventive measures.

Engineer Trainee - Offsite Trading and Tankages

December 2018 - December 2020

- Analyzed and compared design drawings to field status to identify deviations from the basis.
- Participated in developing standard operating procedures for Petroleum products offloading and loading from the ship and transfer to the Product-Day Tank
- Kept the Engineering Manager informed of discipline engineering progress and deviations.
- Supervised job progress from the contractor and sub-contractor, setting deadlines for job completion and following up to ensure completion within the deadline.
- Issued work progress Formats to site engineers and storage in the company's database.

2017/10 - 2018/11 Nigeria

Internal Auditor and Risk Compliance Officer

KPMG NG

- Identified control weaknesses, process inefficiencies, and compliance gaps through detailed testing and analysis.
- Reviewed financial statements, transaction records, and internal processes to ensure accuracy, completeness, and compliance with applicable regulations.
- Developed and maintained productive working relationships with stakeholders to facilitate open communication and collaboration.
- Assisted in the development of audit programs, risk assessment methodologies, and internal control frameworks.

Education

2024/05 - 2024/06 AI Career Essentials

ALX

2023 Professional Certification in Software Engineering

Nigeria ALX

2019 **Master In Chemical Engineering**Nigeria Federal University of Technology, Minna

2014/04 Bachelor Degree in Chemical Engineering

Nigeria Federal University of Technology, Minna

Project Title: Efficiency of Different Fuels On the Thermo-economic Performance of a

200kw

Solid Oxide Fuel Cell Using Thermolib

Projects

africaLand

Our Online-Africa_Land-Gallery aims to create a visually appealing and user-friendly platform to effectively promote and help buyers know the availability of lands in Nigeria.

Store Record, Ecommerce Phone Website

The interface of Store Records is very user friendly making it easy to browse through many items at a time. Store records will help sellers advertise their products to buyers. Order fulfillment will be outsourced to a third-party fulfillment company for increased efficiency

AirBnb-console

This team project is part of the ALX Full-Stack Software Engineering program. It's the first step towards building a first full web application: an AirBnB clone. This first step consists of a custom command-line interface for data management, and the base classes for the storage of this data.

MyBlog

Created a Blog site with features like advance text tools

ecommerce-nextjs

This is a personal Learning project. The e-commerce site is a small site built with React, Next.js, MongoDB for Database, and Stripe for Checkout and Payment

Technical Skill

Lean Six Sigma

Microsoft Office

Frontend and Backend Application development

Excellent communication and teamwork abilities

Process simulation, optimization, and modeling using Aspen HYSYS.

Ability to adapt to tight deadlines and heavy workloads

AI Career Essentials

Javascript/Pyhton

Data Base management

C Language

React/Next.js

HTML/CSS

Certificates

- Certified Project Manager (IPMP) -2014.
- Software Engineering Certificate of Completion

• AI Career Essential